<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation set out by the K. of Spain wherein order is taken for the vse and trafficke of merchandise, with those  of Holland, Zealand and others, aswell by water as by land / truely translated out of the Dutch copy printed at Andwerpe in February last.</title>
            <author>Spain. Sovereign (1556-1598 : Philip II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18464.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33151106</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33151106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1881:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation set out by the K. of Spain wherein order is taken for the vse and trafficke of merchandise, with those  of Holland, Zealand and others, aswell by water as by land / truely translated out of the Dutch copy printed at Andwerpe in February last.</title>
                  <author>Spain. Sovereign (1556-1598 : Philip II)</author>
                  <author>Philip III, King of Spain, 1578-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be sold by William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Belgium --  History --  1555-1648.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
               <term>Spain --  History --  Philip II, 1556-1598.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28930:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28930:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28930:2"/>
            <p>A PROCLAMATION ſet out by the K. of Spaine.</p>
            <p>Wherein order is taken for the vſe and trafficke of merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, with thoſe of Holland Zealand and others, aſwell by water as by land.</p>
            <p>Truely tranſlated out of the Dutch copy printed at Andwerpe in February laſt.</p>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="lat">VBIQVE FLORET</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſold by William Wright. 1592.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:28930:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28930:3"/>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION ſet out by the K. of Spaine.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O our Skout of Andwerp and Markegraue our of land of Reyn or his deputy, gréeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas for to pleaſure our good ſubiects, and to kepe them in the trade and dealing of merchandiſing, Wée are content to permit the aforeſaid dealing with thoſe of Holland and Zealand, &amp; other countries at this preſent being poſſeſſed by our enemies and rebels, for ſo much as concerneth the permitted wares and merchandiſes, which by this our preſent ordinance are not prohibited: in paying certeine dueties of licence, according to the roule thereupon made or yet to be made.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſo it is, That we deſiring herein to ſet downe a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule and order. And hauing therupon had the aduice of our wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued and truſty the perſons of our councell of Eſtates. Haue with the deliberation of our welbeloued &amp; déere Nephue the Duke of Parma and of Plaiſſance, knight of our order, Liefe-tenaunt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, and Captaine Generall of our countries on this ſide, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and doe conſent by theſe preſentes, (vntill otherwiſe therin) ſhalbe ordained, That al and ſingular (aſwel our ſubiects as others) being good and loyall merchants, trading and dealing in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid countries on this ſide, may bring into the ſame out of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid country of Holland Zealand and other like, and carry thether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, all ſortes of wares and merchandiſes, permitted and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, Firſt paying beſides the old and ordinary cuſtomes, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Licences according to the tenor of the roule, thereof made or yet to be made, And that throughout all hauens, ſluſes, and riuers on this ſide, where on our behalfe certaine officers ſhalbe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receiue and collect the ſaid dueties, and that in ſuch manner and order, as on our behalfe in euery place and hauen ſhall be ſet downe and eſtabliſhed, Prouided allwayes that it ſhall not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any merchants or perticular perſons to come hetherwarde from the countries of Holland and Zealand and other like, or to go thetherward, for to bring in or carry out any maner of the aforeſaid
<pb facs="tcp:28930:4"/>
permitted wares and merchandiſes, or otherwiſe without hauinge paſſeport and ſafe conduct for their perſons or factors and dealers with expreſſing the names and ſurnames of them. Which paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports they may obtaine of vs, or of our aforeſaid good Nephue the Duke of Parma &amp;c. Or of him who thereunto on his behalfe ſhalbe aſſigned, and of none other. Prohibiting all gouernours, generals, chiefetaines, captaines, magiſtrates of townes, and other our offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, that they to the effect aforeſaid doe not vndertake to geue any paſſeports or ſafeconductes vnto any whoſoeuer, or to let any body paſſe without our aforeſaid leaue and paſſeport, as is aforeſaid, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of nullity and to be arbitrarily puniſhed, aſwell the perſon which ſhall haue graunted foorth the ſame, as hee who would haue holpen himſelfe therwith. Euen as alſo wee doo ſtraightly prohibite them neither to troble nor moleſt the aforſaid paſſengers, nor alſo to demaund or receiue of them any thinge, either in reſpect of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons nor of the merchandiſes, vpon paine to bee ſeuerely puniſhed. Whereupon we do ordeine our Fiſcall, and all other our Iuſtices and Officers, to take and cauſe to be taken, good and carefull heede to the end this diſorder and abuſe do not breake in further. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome haue preſumed to do to the contrary, Prohibiting all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ships, which ſhall bring hether any merchandiſes from the aforeſaid countries of Holland Zealland and other rebels that they do not take on boorde their ſhips any greater nomber of marinors then they ſhall haue neede of, for the conducting of the ſaid ſhippes. And if any ſhall come ouer apparelled like marriners, and ſhall bee conuicted of any deceit, or to haue done any thing againſt our ſeruice and the common wealth, in ſuch caſe, ſhall aſwell the one as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be puniſhed to the example of others, and their ſhippes forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our vſe. And to the end men may know what merchandiſes are to pay the dueties of Licence. We do declare that all that which ſhall be growen in the Prouinces being in rebellion againſt vs or other places holding with our contrary party, ſhall be ſubiect to pay the ſaid dueties, whether the ſame come from the enemies country, or whether it come by anye other way or country of our obedience euen as alſo all that which ſhall paſſe by water or by lande, through the Iuriſdictions and limits of the aforeſaide countries and prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (holding part with our enemies) ſhall be reputed and taken to come from the enemy, or that which with ſhips of the enemy ſhall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be
<pb facs="tcp:28930:4"/>
brought hether, though ſo it were that the ſame were done with paſſeporte from vs, or of our aforeſaide good Nephew the Duke of Parma &amp;c. And alſo all that which ſhall paſſe through the aforeſaid countries (taking part againſt vs) ſhall be reputed to goe to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
            <p>And to the end all men may know what Marchandiſes are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and may not be carried out of our ſaid countries, we doo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the ſame to be, all ſorts of Armor &amp; munitions of warre, corn, and vittels, Bell mettle, and mettle, Teaſels, Hops, Barkes of trees, Flax, thred of Flax, and of wooſted, Talwood as of Oake-trées, Elme trées and Aſhtrees. And touching the marchandizes which we will not to be brought hither, are theſe following, to wit: All clothes, ſtammels, and generallie all commodities of wollen, worſted and linnen, wrought and made in England, Holland, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and like prouinces. And forſomuch as by our ſaide rebelles, hinderance is doone in the repairing and maintaining of the banks on this ſide: we will and declare, that as long as ſuche hinderance ſhall continue, it ſhal not be lawfull for any, to carrie out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of our obedience, vnto our aforeſaid rebels any ſorts of wood Bauin wood, ſtones and other materials, ſeruing for the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and maintaining of the banks on their ſide, euen as alſo it ſhal not be lawfull for any one to bring or cauſe to be brought hither, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny white or refined ſalt, vnleſſe he do alſo bring with him like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of bay ſalte. Which duties and licence (euen as they are or ſhall be ſpecified in the rowle therevpon made or to bee made) the Collectors and Controulers ſhall not in any manner exceed, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue more, vppon paine to bee depoſed from their offices, and to pay the Quadruple value to our vſe, and to reſtore vnto the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants or others, that which they vndulie ſhall haue receiued. It ſhall be lawfull for the aforeſaid officers, as often as they ſhal think good, to cauſe the marchants, Marinors, and others, which ſhall at any time conduct any Marchandizes, to verefie that which they ſhall haue entred, vpon paine (in caſe of deniall) that they ſhall bee reputed guiltie and culpable of that which ſhall be propoſed againſt them. And to the ende the ſaid officers may the better and without deceit and ſuſpition attend theyr callings, it ſhall not be lawfull for them, to meddle with any marchandizes, or factorie, nor to haue part or portion with any marchants, Farmers of our cuſtomes, or
<pb facs="tcp:28930:5"/>
others vſing trade, muchleſſe ſhall it be lawful for them to keepe a Tauerne and ſell wine or béere, vpon paine of loaſing their offices, and to be Arbitrarilie puniſhed. Prohibiting and defending al mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſhips, and carriers, in their ſhips waggons or other veſſels, to lade or vnlade, any Marchandizes or wares, without hauing firſt paid the dutie of the aforeſaid licences vnto the Collectors thervnto committed: who in this caſe, ſhall giue vnto euery Marchant a hil, containing good and ample ſpecification of all the parcels of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, which they will lade or vnlade togither, alſo the ſumme paide for the ſame, and ſhall be ſubſcribed by the aforeſaid Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and other officers therevnto ordained and ſealed, if any ſeale be therevnto appointed. Which bill the ſaide Marchants ſhall be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to exhibite or ſhew vnto the Controuler, before it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to tranſport the ſaid marchandizes from any place or Hauen. And the ſaid Controuler ſhalbe bound, therof to keepe good account, to keepe the ſame bils in his poſſeſſion, and to keep counterroule of the ſummes therein, according to theſe inſtructions. And if it ſhall be found, that any fraud or abuſe be committed by the marchants, Factors, Shipmaiſters, Carriers, or others, as in being departed, without hauing paid the dutie of the aforeſaide Licence, or hauinge entred one thing for another. We will that ſuch wares and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes ſhall be by the officers of our aforeſaide Licences, ſeized on, and confiſcated according to the ſaide proclamation. And if the ſame or the like were committed by the Shipmaiſters, or carriers, vnto whom the marchandizes doo not apperteine. And that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſaid Shipmaiſters and Carriers, had put in practiſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, ſaile away, or vnlade, and to ſéeke any vnwoonted way with out hauing entred or aduiſed our aforeſaid officers of the Licences thereof, and ſatiſfied them, according to the order heere before ſette down: In ſuch caſe their Ships, Waggons, &amp; horſſe, ſhalbe confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, whether the ſame do appertaine vnto them or no. And ſhall there beſides forfait the ſumme of one hundred pounds of xl. pence Flemiſh the pounds. Prohibiting moreouer, all and ſingular of what qualitie they be, to wrong, iniurie, reuile, moleſt, or ſlander in any manner of wiſe ſoeuer, any of the Committées, or officers of the ſaid Licences, vpon like paine of one hundred pounds, for euery time, and to be arbitrarilie puniſhed. Conſidering that all the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:28930:5"/>
officers haue beene retained (euen as we in effect doo retaine them by theſe preſents, in ſo much as concerneth their offices and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) vnder our protection and tuition. And therefore we doo charge and ordaine all gouernors, Captaines, Maieſtrates and officers, to aſſiſt, protect, and defend them, againſt the ſaid iniuries, troubles, moleſtations, and hinderances, which might be doone vnto them.</p>
            <p>And to the end none pretend ignorance of all the points and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles aforeſaid: we doo will and command you, that you preſently and without delay, cauſe the ſame to be made knowne, proclaimed, and publiſhed, within our Towne of Antwerp, and limits of your iuriſdiction, where néede ſhall require, and you ſhall finde to apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. And for the kéeping and obſeruing thereof, do you procéede and cauſe to be procéeded againſt the tranſgreſſors and diſobedient, by the execution of the penalties, forfaitures, and fines aforeſayde, without fauour, diſſimulation, or delaie: for the dooing whereof, we do giue you full power, aucthoritie, and ſpeciall charge.</p>
            <p>Willing and commanding, all and ſingular, that they unto you in dooing the ſame be dilligent and obedient, For ſo it pleaſeth vs.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Geuen in our Towne of Bruſſels, vnder our Cruterſeale therevpon Printed Subſcribed <date>the ſixt of December, 1591.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By the King in his Councell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Publiſhed in our Tovvne of Andvverp the xi. of February. 1592.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
